William F. Heavey Papers
William F. Heavey Papers
1934-1964
Heavey, William Francis, 1896-1974.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American brigadier-general, engineer. Collection includes correspondence (1942-1964); biographical material; manuscript essays; and articles and clippings by and about Heavey.
149044
Biographical History
William Francis Heavey (1896-1974) was an American military officer who retired with the rank of Brigadier-General.
Heavey was born in Fort McPherson, Georgia on January 29, 1896, the son of Brigadier-General John W. Heavey, he graduated from the U.S. Military Academy at West Point in 1917. During World War I Heavey was assigned to the Army Corps of Engineers as a second lieutenant; he was quickly promoted to captain (1917) and then major (1918), and commanded the 2d Engineer Special Brigade in fifty amphibious landings in the southwest Pacific and Philippines.
After World War I he studied at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, earning his degree in 1922, and a few years later (1938) graduated from the Command and General Staff School. He was promoted to brigadier-general in 1942, and during World War II he was Chief Engineering Officer for IV Corps (1941-1942) and Commanding General of the 2d Engineer Amphibian Brigade, South Pacific Command (1942-1946).
For his services he was decorated with Oak Leaf Cluster and the Bronze Star. He was a charter member of the American Society of Military Engineers, and authored the book Down ramp! The story of the Army Amphibian engineers (1947). He and his wife had two children; their son William F. Heavey, Jr. (1920-1987) attended the U.S. Naval Academy and became a naval aviator.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William F. Heavey Papers consist of biographical material about Heavey's career, correspondence (incoming and outgoing), subject files (mostly memorabilia), manuscripts (articles by and about Heavey), and published material (books by and about Heavey, book reviews, and some clippings about Heavey and others).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. All other material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Heavey, William Francis, 1896-1974.; United States. -- Army -- Officers -- Biography.; Generals -- United States.; Military engineering.; Military engineers -- United States.; United States -- History, Military -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Engineers.; Generals.; Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1942; 1945,; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1942; 1943 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Directory, 1960; 2 ESB Vets Assoc. (Box 1)
  - Distinguished Visitor Award, in Spanish (Box 1)
  - Field order, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Citizens Award, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Photograph, Heavey and Noce, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Recommendation for award, 1945 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles by
    - Army vs. Navy, undated (Box 1)
    - Father made the first Army team, undated (Box 1)
  - Contribution to Reader's Digest (Box 1)
  - Promotion article, undated (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Books by
    - Abajo la rampa, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Down ramp, 1947 (Box 1)
    - History of the Second Engineer Special Brigade, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Map and aerial photo reading, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Books about
    - Amphibian engineer operations (volume IV of the series, Engineers of the Southwest Pacific), 1959 (Box 2)
  - Book reviews
    - New York Times Book Review, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Magazines with articles about
    - Yale Review, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Magazines with articles by
    - Engineering News-Record, 1934 (Box 2)
    - The Houston Port Book, 1952; 2 issues (Box 2)
    - The Military Engineer, 1946; 1948; 4 issues (Box 2)
  - Magazines with articles about others
    - Time, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About Heavey, 1948 (Box 2)
    - About Heavey and others, 1945; 1948,; undated (Box 2)